Guide to the John Killam Murphy Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Killam Murphy papers
1893-1933
MS 1402
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(2 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, photographs, papers, and other materials relating to Murphy's nautical interests and career with the naval reserve forces and the U.S. Coast Guard in New Haven, Connecticut. Murphy participated in naval operations during the Spanish American War, and World Wars I and II.
Murphy, John Killam, 1875-1969
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. William Welch Gaines and Alexander K. Murphy, 1985 and 1988.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. General Correspondence, 1916-1933. II. Topical Files, 1893-1927.
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence, photographs, writings, and other material documenting the naval career of John Killam Murphy. Murphy spent thirty-three years of service in the United States Navy, Naval Reserve, Coast Guard, and Connecticut Naval Militia.
The John Killam Murphy Papers were donated to Yale University Library in 1985 by Mrs. William Welch Gaines and Alexander K. Murphy.
The papers are arranged in two series:
I. General Correspondence, 1916-1933
II. Topical Files, 1893-1972
SERIES I, GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, 1916-1933 contains letters relating to Murphy's naval reserve duty as Commander of Section Base 1, Third Naval District, which was headquartered in New Haven, Connecticut. This series also contains material relating to Murphy's command of Eagle 27, a ship used to train naval reservists from 1921-1925. Letters from the 1930s concern Murphy's lifelong activities as a yachtsman.
SERIES II, TOPICAL FILES, 1893-1927 contains a small quantity of student papers from Murphy's Yale University years. The bulk of material in this series concerns naval topics, including the Naval Reserve bill, Navy Day celebrations in New Haven, and photographs of ships and the New Haven harbor.
Biographical / Historical
John Killam Murphy was born on March 21, 1875 in New Haven, Connecticut. He graduated from Yale University in 1898 (Ph.B.). Murphy spent thirty-three years in the service of the United States Navy, Naval Reserve, Coast Guard, and Connecticut Naval Militia. He saw duty in the Spanish - American War, World War I, and World War II. Murphy trained naval reservists in New Haven (1921-1925) and during World War II. He was also a lifelong yachtsman and Yacht designer who died in August, 1969 in West Haven.
New Haven (Conn.); United States -- Naval reserves; Murphy, John Killam, 1875-1969; United States Coast Guard
- General Correspondence, 1916-1929, 1933, undated; Series I; 0.5; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  The materials in this series are arranged chronologically.
  - General correspondence, 1916-1929, 1933, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-13)
- Topical Files, 1893, 1921-1927, undated; Series II; 0.5; (1 box)
  The materials in this series are arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Naval Reserve Bill, 1921-1923, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Navigation, 1923-1926, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Navy Day celebrations in New Haven, 1925-1927 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Photographs: Section Base No. 1, New Haven Harbor; U.S.S. Elfrida; Various individuals, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    General note
    See also: CF82
  - Photograph: USS Reed (Box 3)
  - United States Naval Reserve Force. Third Naval District, New Haven, Connecticut, 1917-1919 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Writings, lectures, plans, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Yale University: student papers, 1893, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)